Guide to the Paul Nash Letters to Mercia Oakley
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Paul Nash Letters to Mercia Oakley
1909-1951
1909-1912
MSS 24
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
.5
1 box
This collection comprises letters from Paul Nash to Mercia Oakley, written from 1909 to 1918.
Nash, Paul, 1889-1946
Biographical / Historical
The painter, printmaker, and designer Paul Nash (1899-1946) was born in London and raised in Iver Heath, Buckinghamshire. He trained as an illustrator at Chelsea Polytechnic and the London County Council's Bolt Court Art School, before enrolling at the Slade School. Nash initially found some success as a bookplate designer. His work from this early period heavily references the British Pre-Raphaelites. Nash sought to fashion himself as a "Painter-Poet," in the tradition of such figures as Dante Rossetti and William Blake. Nash opened his first solo show in November 1912 at the Carfax Gallery in London, which appears to have been well received. It was through this exhibition that he would become acquainted with the critic and painter Roger Fry. Throughout his career, Nash's work was characterized by dark overtones and often literary themes. The English landscape was a recurring theme in Nash's work, often inflected with elements of the political atmosphere of the times. Beginning in the 1920s, Nash worked within something of a surrealist paradigm, which would become even more pronounced during his World War II era art.
At the outbreak of World War I, Nash enlisted in the Artists' Rifles for home service. In March 1917, he was sent to the front. He was injured in a fall in May 1917, but returned to Ypres Salient as an official war artist in November 1917. His work from this period focused on the effect of war on the landscape. In May 1918, he staged the exhibition "Void of War" at the Leicester Galleries, which led to further painting commissions from the Ministry of Information. Nash also served as official war artist during the Second World War, when he was assigned by The War Artists' Advisory Committee to the Air Ministry and then the Ministry of Information. In his World War II work, Nash engaged frequently with themes of military technology and destruction. Nash began writing his autobiography, Outline, in 1936 or 1937, but it remained unpublished until 1949 when Faber and Faber released it posthumously. Nash died of heart failure in 1946. In 1948, the Tate Gallery, London held a major memorial exhibition of his work.
The recipient of Nash's letters, Mercia Oakley was a close friend and confident of the painter. They met as children through Oakley's godmother, Mrs. George Grimsdale, a neighbor of the Nash family at Iver Heath. Oakley appears to have spent significant time at the Grimsdale's home, Wings. George Grimsdale was one of Nash's earliest patrons, commissioning a bookplate in 1916. The relationship between Nash and Oakley is ambiguous. Clearly quite intimate, they appear to have never been romantic partners, though many letters reference this possibility. Oakley married the Grimsdale's nephew Gerald in 1916.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Fund
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: I. Letters from Paul Nash to Mercia Oakley; II. Miscellaneous. The letters are arranged chronologically, with some letters dated according to their postmark when the letter is undated.
The numbering of letters (1-51) is aligned with the numbering in Dear Mercia.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises 51 letters from Paul Nash to Mercia Oakley. The letters date from 1909 to early 1918, with many undated and the vast majority dating from 1909 to 1912. The letters from Oakley to Nash do not appear to have survived. In a primarily playful and intimate tone, the correspondence addresses a range of themes related mostly to Oakley and Nash's personal lives. The letters verge on stream-of-consciousness, skipping rapidly between subjects. Many focus on the often confusing dynamics within their friendship and Nash's philosophies toward life and art. Others speak to more quotidian things, such as social events, family news, and travel plans. The letters taper off extensively when Nash meets his eventual wife, Margaret Odeh, in 1913. The collection's latest letters address both Nash and Oakley's weddings and speak briefly of Nash's work as an Official War Artist during the First World War.
The collection provides some intimate insight into Nash's feelings toward the development of his career. He expresses excitement over his studies and successes, as well as disappointment over failed commissions. In 1912, Nash writes extensively of his preparations for his first exhibition at the Carfax & Co., London. He addresses both the exhibition logistics and his expectations surrounding the event. Nash also writes of exhibitions he has seen, as well as books and poetry he has read. Many of the letters are illustrated with playful, often comical sketches, frequently picturing imagined encounters between Nash and Oakley or illustrating humorous anecdotes. Some letters are accompanied by their original envelope.
Existence and Location of Copies
The letters are transcribed in their entirety in: Dear Mercia: Paul Nash letters to Mercia Oakley, 1909-18, edited by Janet Boulton. Wakefield: Fleece Press, 1991.
See: http://hdl.handle.net/10079/bibid/3246799
Dear Mercia also reproduces the illustrations that accompany Nash's letters in the present collection.
Bookplate designers -- Great Britain; Bookplates -- Great Britain; Landscape painters -- Great Britain; Painters -- Great Britain; Painting -- Great Britain; Painting, British -- 20th Century; World War, 1914-1918; Humorous pictures; Pen and ink drawings; Letters; Photographs; Poems; Bottomley, Gordon, 1874-1948; Brooks, Ivan Wilkinson, 1891-1952; Lee, Rupert, 1887-1959; Monck, Walter Nugent Bligh, 1878-1958; Nash, Barbara; Nash, John, 1893-1977; Nash, Margaret Theodosia, 1887-1960; Nash, Paul, 1889-1946 -- Correspondence; Nash, Paul, 1889-1946 -- Exhibitions; Nash, William Harry, -1929; Oakley, Mercia -- Correspondence; Richmond, W. B., Sir (William Blake), 1842-1921; Seutoni, Veré; Carfax & Co; Slade School of Fine Art
- Letters, Nash, Paul, 1889-1946
  Correspondence; Nash, Paul, 1889-1946 -- Correspondence; Oakley, Mercia -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1909 March 29; 3 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter: 18 x 23 cm (Box Nash 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash belatedly thanks Mercia for singing to him. In postscript, Nash writes that he has "done good today" because he has been telling children fairy tales.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1909 September 10; 4 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 18 x 23 cm (Box Nash 2)
    Written from Iver Heath. Includes a sketch in ink entitled "is it raining?" (reproduced in Dear Merci a, p. 23). Discusses visits and golf.
    Pen and ink drawings
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910 February 6; 3 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 15 x 23 cm (Box Nash 3)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Nash makes plans for visiting Oakley. Includes ink drawing entitled "Mercia writing letters with her nose" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, p. 24).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910 April 15; 4 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 15 x 23 cm (Box Nash 4)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Nash thanks Oakley for recommending Nash to her hostess, though Nash remains unclear whether the recommendation was "upon the virtues of my work or the virtues of my character!" Asks Oakley if she wishes to be sent any of his work beyond the bookplates she has already received.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910 April 16; 3 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 15 x 22 cm (Box Nash 5)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Nash comments on Oakley's crossness in her last letter. Concerns details of a sketch Oakley has requested.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910 May 6; 3 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 18 x 23 cm (Box Nash 6)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Nash requests permission to visit Oakley on Saturday. Discusses thoughts in springtime and urges Oakley, "why worry!" People mentioned: Jack (John Northcote Nash).
    Nash, John, 1893-1977
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 23 x 18 cm (Box Nash 7)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Nash thanks Oakley for inviting him to visit but assures her again that he cannot come, much as he wishes to see her.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910; 4 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 18 x 23 cm (Box Nash 8)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Written in black and orange ink. Nash thanks Oakley for being angry on his behalf. Includes a sketch of Nash on one knee kissing Oakley's fingertips and another depicting Oakley pulling Nash's leg (reproduced in Dear Mercia, pages 28-29).
    Pen and ink drawings; Bookplates -- Great Britain
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910; 4 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 15 x 20 cm (Box Nash 9)
    Written from South Kensington. Black bordered. Nash discusses a story related in Oakley's previous letter concerning Oakley's mother and a swallow. Further discusses birds and mention's Nash's trip to "the Exhibition".
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910 July 21; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 23 x 18 cm (Box Nash 10)
    A commission Oakley secured for Nash from a Mrs. Wilson (?) went badly and Nash worries that Oakley will consider him "a great rotter." Nash looks forward to meeting artists and writers in order to "get known" and enter "the select circles where he longs to move one day." He is still making bookplates, but is starting to make other types of art as well. The letter ends in a discussion of the books he and Oakley have lent each other. People mentioned: Mrs. Wilson(?).
    Bookplates -- Great Britain
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 23 x 18 cm (Box Nash 11)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash comforts Oakley about her friend who "did back-street things" and assures her that it was not her fault. Nash writes that he is trying to earn the money necessary to go to the Slade School in October. He adds that he makes "bookplates for money & studies for his salvation".
    Bookplates -- Great Britain; Slade School of Fine Art
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910 October 6; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 23 x 18 cm (Box Nash 12)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Concerns the material in Oakley's last letter. Nash adds that he begins work at the Slade School on Wednesday. Includes two sketches, the first entitled "Injured Innocence (in no sense)" and the second with the caption "Arise, fair maiden from these penitent genuflections" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, pages 33 and 34).
    Pen and ink drawings; Slade School of Fine Art
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910 October 15; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 23 x 18 cm (Box Nash 13)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Tells Oakley that he enjoyed visiting her. Includes a sketch entitled, "vague departure of Paul" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, p. 35).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1910 December 25; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 20 cm (Box Nash 14)
    Written from Iver Heath. Apologizes that he cannot afford Christmas presents and discusses political leanings.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 January 4; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 23 x 18 cm (Box Nash 15)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Concerns Nash's inability to accept Oakley's invitation, due to other commitments. Nash explains that he is "trying to do everything and the work is suffering." He also apologizes for inadvertently offending Oakley's mother.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 23 x 18 cm (Box Nash 16)
    Written from Iver Heath. Black bordered. Nash admonishes Oakley against including "sudden shocks" in her letters. Humorously explains the domestic drama that ensued upon his reading in her last letter that she "immediately fell head over ears in love." People mentioned: Mrs. Caswell, Mrs. Peddell, Peddell the manservant, Barbara Nash, John Nash, and W. H. Nash.
    Nash, John, 1893-1977; Nash, Barbara; Nash, William Harry, -1929
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 September 23; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 20 cm (Box Nash 17)
    Written from Iver Heath. Concerns a house party in the country and describes the landscape and Nash's first experience fowling. Also mentions the visit of Nash's friend, who is in love. Nash discusses his desire to become famous, but explains that his first goal is to become independent of his father. Includes two sketches, the first of a staircase and the second of a man holding a smoking gun (reproduced in Dear Mercia, opposite p. 41). People mentioned: Barbara (Nash?).
    Hunting; Nash, William Harry, -1929; Nash, Barbara
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 18 cm (Box Nash 18)
    Written from Chelsea. Nash thanks Oakley for the key to his door. The letter continues on a humorous note and ends, "Yrs till two black guineapigs produce one white ten & sixpenny sow."
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 4 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 24 x 20 cm (Box Nash 19)
    Written from Chelsea. Concerns Oakley's injured ankle, two dances, and the comforting effects of nature. Quotes two poems and includes two sketches--one of upside down dancers and the other of Nash dressed as a pirate (reproduced in Dear Mercia, pages 43 and 45).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 20)
    Written from Chelsea. Concerns plans to visit the Oakleys and includes a drawing of a man and woman with the caption, "good foot?" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, p. 47).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912 January?; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 21)
    Written from Iver Heath. Discusses amusements in London. Nash is sending Oakley a proof of one of his etchings and wishes to bring Jack to visit her.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 10 x 15 cm (Box Nash 22)
    Discusses a cricket match. Seems to be a fragment of a longer letter. People mentioned: Wilkie (Ivan Wilkinson Brooks).
    Brooks, Ivan Wilkinson, 1891-1952
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 18 x 13 cm (Box Nash 23)
    Concerns Nash's poetry. Fragment of a longer letter.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 20 x 15 cm (Box Nash 24)
    Nash scolds Oakley for forgetting about him. Includes a self-portrait (reproduced in Dear Mercia, page 50).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 25)
    Written from Iver Heath. Discusses luggage. Includes drawing with caption, "Donkey Timms" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, p. 51).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 26)
    Written from Chelsea. Nash expresses gratitude that Oakley will introduce him to "artistic shelter-giving Aunts" and plans costumes for a dance. Ends "Adieu. I enclose a picture, show it not at the breakfast table give it eventually to the dog."
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 4 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 20 x 25 cm (Box Nash 27)
    Nash asks who "Aunt Kate" is and mentions the "prophet in London noise." Discusses Oakley's singing and requests to draw her hands when she gets back from Scotland. Includes an ink drawing entitled "You should have seen us going down the Strand last night!" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, page 53). People mentioned: Aunt Kate and Wilkie.
    Pen and ink drawings; Brooks, Ivan Wilkinson, 1891-1952
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 28)
    Discusses Nash's feelings under the stars, his stay at "Wings," and his poetry. People mentioned: Oakley's "nuncle", Morgan, Oakley's mother, and Clark.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1911 or 1912; 3 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 18 x 23 cm (Box Nash 29)
    Written from Wallingford. Mentions photos and requests a visit. Includes two ink drawings, one entitled "Portrait of the late Dr Barnarnars" and the other depicting a marching army being showered with roses (reproduced in Dear Mercia, pages 57-58).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912 March 5; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 21 cm (Box Nash 30)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash urges Oakley to visit Chelsea. Quotes several poems and includes an ink drawing (reproduced in Dear Mercia, page 60). People mentioned: Wilkie (Ivan Wilkinson Brooks).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912 March 15; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 31)
    Written from Iver Heath. Discusses various matters. Nash has been unlucky in love, writing that he "broke his dream" because he has "been in love with an idea." Includes envelope with drawing of "Aunt Sam?". People mentioned: Lavengro (Rupert Lee) and an unnamed girl.
    Pen and ink drawings; Lee, Rupert, 1887-1959
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 6 pages (3 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 21 cm (Box Nash 32)
    Written from Chelsea. Begins with a poem by Nash about Oakley. Nash discusses the emotional toll of his recent breakup and expresses the comfort he finds in the friendship of his "sister" Oakley.
    Poems
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 6 pages (3 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 20 cm (Box Nash 33)
    Written from Iver Heath. Quotes Edgar Allen Poe and discusses the beauty of the night and Nash's sudden introduction to Mlle. Seutoni. People mentioned: Gordon Bottomley, Jack, Wilkie and Mlle. Vere Seutoni.
    Nash, John, 1893-1977; Brooks, Ivan Wilkinson, 1891-1952; Bottomley, Gordon, 1874-1948
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 34)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash's father has been ill. Discusses hands and plans for future drawings and includes a poem written by Nash. People mentioned: William Harry Nash, Sir William Richmond, and Lavengro (Rupert Lee).
    Poems; Lee, Rupert, 1887-1959; Nash, William Harry, -1929; Richmond, W. B. (William Blake), Sir, 1842-1921
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 5 pages (3 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 35)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash mentions plans to travel to Paris soon and discusses drawing. Nash writes, "I want a drastic, desperate change, a shock of some sort so fierce violent soul-shaking" and he complains that he has yet to find success in his profession. Nash also describes a day he spent with Vere. Includes a smaller sheet with the heading "Facts". People mentioned: Ivan Wilkinson Brooks, Miss Hogan, and Vere Seutoni.
    Brooks, Ivan Wilkinson, 1891-1952; Seutoni, Veré
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 36)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash urges Oakley not to become romantically involved with a student of mathematics. Nash discusses his jealousy and explains that he and Wilkie have had a fight over Vere Seutoni, who thinks she is in love with Nash. Nash says he will no longer be able to visit Paris and hopes to visit Oakley instead. He also discusses the "Green Lady". Includes an ink drawing entitled, "Brother Paul, or, The Monk and the Woman" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, p. 77).
    Pen and ink drawings; Brooks, Ivan Wilkinson, 1891-1952; Seutoni, Veré
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 3 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 20 x 25 cm (Box Nash 37)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash discusses his arrangements in town and hopes Oakley will soon visit. People mentioned: Vere Seutoni and Rupert Lee.
    Lee, Rupert, 1887-1959; Seutoni, Veré
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912 May 12; 4 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 20 x 25 cm (Box Nash 38)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash and Wilkie have resolved their dispute and Nash is going to display his drawings in a London gallery. Nash now thinks he will visit Paris after all. Includes ink drawing of a woman with an umbrella and a bus with an ad for "Paul's Pictures" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, p. 80). People mentioned: Ivan Wilkinson Brooks and Sir W.B. Richmond.
    Pen and ink drawings; Brooks, Ivan Wilkinson, 1891-1952; Richmond, W. B. (William Blake), Sir, 1842-1921
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912 July; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 39)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash has been busy and completed three landscapes. He hopes that Oakley will pose for another picture. He also discusses potential art sales. Includes ink drawing of a reclining woman (reproduced in Dear Mercia, p. 81). People mentioned: Nash's uncle, Nugent Monck (producer of the Norwich Players), Gordon Bottomley, John Nash, and Aunt Jane.
    Pen and ink drawings; Bottomley, Gordon, 1874-1948; Monck, Walter Nugent Bligh, 1878-1958; Nash, John, 1893-1977
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 40)
    Written from Iver Heath. Concerns Nash's upcoming show at the Carfax Gallery in London.
    Carfax & Co
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 20 cm (Box Nash 41)
    Written from Chelsea. Nash insists that Oakley should be in London on November 7 to come to the private viewing of Nash's show. People mentioned: Oakley's mother and father, Rupert Lee.
    Lee, Rupert, 1887-1959
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 23 x 18 cm (Box Nash 42)
    Includes ink drawing entitled: "All I really remember of our dinner last night at the 'Gourmet'!" (reproduced in Dear Mercia, p. 86).
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912 or 1913; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 25 x 20 cm (Box Nash 43)
    Concerns the previous letter Nash sent to Oakley.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912 or 1913; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 20 cm (Box Nash 44)
    Nash apologizes for his behavior when last they met. Nash wishes he and Oakley could have fallen in love with each other rather than with people who don't love them back.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912 or 1913; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 18 cm (Box Nash 45)
    Nash explains that he is innocent and did not mean to offend Oakley.
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1912 or 1913; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 26 x 18 cm (Box Nash 46)
    Reminisces about Wings and consoles Oakley about her "heart-ache."
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1913 March 29; 3 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 20 x 16 cm (Box Nash 47)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash thanks Oakley for her letter and apologizes for being unable to send a longer reply. Nash is in love. Includes envelope. People mentioned: Margaret Odeh (Nash's future wife), Oakley's mother.
    Nash, Margaret Theodosia, 1887-1960
  - Letter to Mercia Oakley, 1914 December 4; 3 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed: 20 x 26 cm (Box Nash 48)
    Written from Iver Heath. Nash announces his plans to marry on December 17, 1914, and his acceptance into military service. Nash hates the war, writing, "never was there such world-amazing nonsense may it gasp itself lifeless before two years are out." Includes envelope. People mentioned: Margaret Odeh.
    World War, 1914-1918; Nash, Margaret Theodosia, 1887-1960